<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>metagenomics | CHTsai</title><link>https://chtsai0105.github.io/tag/metagenomics/</link><atom:link href="https://chtsai0105.github.io/tag/metagenomics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>metagenomics</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 22:48:23 -0700</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://chtsai0105.github.io/media/icon_hue12033e7bcbf2b7513dbeb90bca8f915_21606_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>metagenomics</title><link>https://chtsai0105.github.io/tag/metagenomics/</link></image><item><title>dbcanLight</title><link>https://chtsai0105.github.io/project/dbcanlight/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 22:48:23 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://chtsai0105.github.io/project/dbcanlight/</guid><description>&lt;p>Functional annotation is an important step in genome/metagenome projects. It give us hints of what these
genes are capable of. One of the widely used functional database is CAZy (Carbohydrate-Active enZYmes), which
describes the enzymes that degrade, modify, or create glycosidic bonds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, most of the users access the CAZy database through the tool &lt;a href="https://github.com/linnabrown/run_dbcan" target="_blank" rel="noopener">run_dbcan&lt;/a>,
which is able to identify the CAZymes and even the potential substrates of a given peptide sequence. However,
the hmmscan it use for the searching step is not very efficient and are quite time consuming when the querying/searching
database is huge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To improve the performance, I re-designed the program, utilized pyhmmer, a python bindings to HMMER3, to develop a
lightweight version - &lt;a href="dbcanLight">dbcanLight&lt;/a>. It reimplemented the cazyme and substrate search processes with
hmmsearch and highly improve the speed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We benchmarked on a protein fasta with 9,360 sequences. 3 rounds of tests have been run on cazyme detection mode
(&amp;ndash;tools hmmer in run_dbcan and -m cazyme in dbcanLight) and 1 round of test have been run on substrate detection
mode (&amp;ndash;tools dbcansub in run_dbcan and -m sub in dbcanLight). Our tool accelates 10X in substrate detection and
almost 20X in cazyme detection. Moreover, the outputs are fully compatible with the original version.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in dbcanLight, please refer to the &lt;a href="dbcanLight">GitHub page&lt;/a>
for more details.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Metagenomics</title><link>https://chtsai0105.github.io/project/metagenomics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 23:18:17 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://chtsai0105.github.io/project/metagenomics/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are 2 major metagenomic approaches to investigate the microbiome - amplicon sequencing and shotgun
sequencing. The major aim for amplicon-based approach is estimate the relative abundance of each species
in the sample. For shotgun-based method, we can retrieve the metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs) and
further interrogate the functional capacity of them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, we apply metagenomic techniques to 2 ongoing projects - The citrus huanglongbing (HLB) project
and elk coprophilous microbiome project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the citrus HLB project, we aim to find out how the citurs rhizosphere microbiome change during the HLB
progression. It have been observed that the HLB-infected citrus trees suffered from root decline. In
previous studies, we also confirmed that the HLB infection resulted in a different microbiome pattern in
citrus rhizosphere. Our goal is to track the rhizosphere microbiome alteration and further looking for the
functional changes during the HLB progression. Hopefully we will know more about the association between
the rhizosphere microbiome and the HLB-related root decline symptom.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the coprophilous microbiome project, we use the elk dung as a model system to observe the succession
process. During the decomposition of dung, the microbiome utlize the nutrient resources and further change
the nutritional condition and temperature, which in turn drive the succession of microbiome. The elk dung
pellets were collected in a series of time points. The data was been analyse through both amplicon and
shotgun approaches to reveal the populational change in coprophilous microbiome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sicne the shotgun metagenomic analysis usually contains several steps, we also developed a snakemake
workflow to process the data. Please refer to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/chtsai0105/smk-metagenome" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub page&lt;/a>
for more details. Note that the workflow is still under development and is subject to change.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>